# 北方人吃笋吃的少
People in the north rarely eat bamboo shoots
# 有很多人也不知道怎么做
A lot of people do not know how to cook either
# 咱们要做一个干烧冬笋
We are going to cook 'dry-braised winter bamboo shoots'
# 你看雪里蕻的叶
Look. The leaves of pickled potherb mustard
# 经过这一炸你看 酥脆
So crispy after frying
# 这个是应季的
This is seasonal food
# 先剌一刀给剌一刀剥皮
Cut it first to remove the skin
# 外皮很老
The outer skin is very hard and chewy
# 但是越剥里边就越嫩了
But it becomes tender inside as you peel it
# 这个皮有几个说法
There are some issues about the skin
# 这边的皮
The skin in this part
# 就像这一块的皮
For example, here
# 这可以做菜的
You can use it in some dishes
# 这个皮
The skin here
# 这叫笋衣
is named 'bamboo shoot clothes'
# 你像比如我们做的酸辣汤
For example, in sour-spicy soup
# 搁点豆腐片
You may add some sliced tofu
# 笋衣片
and 'bamboo shoot clothes'
# 这个特别嫩 好东西
This is very tender. Good stuff
# 可以直接吃吗
Can we eat it raw?
# 不能直接吃 一会还得处理一下
Nope, we need to process it later
# 我们把这笋给它修成这种窝头状
Cut the bamboo shoot into the shape of 'wo tou' (steamed corn bread)
# 外边刮得光溜的
Shave the outside until smooth
# 我们给它煮上
Let's boil it
# 凉水热水都行
Either cold or hot water
# 煮15分钟
Boil it for 15 minutes
# 这边煮着咱们切点小料
Let's cut some ingredients while boiling the bamboo shoot
# 雪菜
(Pickled) Potherb mustard
# 把这雪菜叶展开
Spread the leaf
# 一炸垫底下碧绿碧绿的倍漂亮
Fry it and put under the dish. It's beautifully green
# 老师傅老手法
Old chef, old cooking style
# 这梗别太多 太多它咸
Don't add too much stem, otherwise it's gonna be too salty
# 这雪菜用的时候呢
Before adding into the dish
# 要洗洗它 泡泡它
You need to wash it and soak it
# 切成小丁状
Cut into small dices
# 别死乞白赖挤
But don't squeeze it too much
# 要吃雪菜的脆嫩
you want it to be crunchy and tender
# 要把这水都给挤干了
If you squeeze out all the water
# 它就不脆了
It's not crunchy any more
# 咱们这边煮着
While boiling
# 这边可以炸雪菜了
We can start frying the pickled potherb mustard
# 油温四成热
Oil temperature is 120 degrees Celsius
# 你看啊
Look
# 立马就伸展开了
The leaves spread immediately
# 炸的是雪菜叶 碧绿碧绿的
The fried leaves are beautifully green
# 好看吧 行
Looks nice? Yeah
# 好了大爷 行了
That's done, Da Ye. Okay
# 先关火 这边晾着
Turn off the fire. Cool it a bit
# 晾完了它才酥脆
The leaves will be crispy after cooling down
# 冬笋好了
Bamboo shoot is done
# 因为你没煮的时候
If you do not boil it (before cutting)
# 一切它就容易炸了
The shoot is going to crack once you cut it
# 就不容易出刀口
In that case, it's not beautiful
# 现在煮完了以后你看
Now, after boiling
# 一看就透了
You can easily cut through it
# 在大爷学堂里面有个刀工叫劈柴块
There is a special cutting skill, 'chop-wood' cut
# 什么叫劈柴块
What is a 'chop-wood' cut?
# 看着啊 不是切了
Look. This is not all about cutting
# 要把它这个丝纹路给拍松
You need to crack it through the fibers
# 现在已经松了你看
Now there's a crack
# 隋坡你看着啊
Look, Sui Po
# 剌开一口
Cut it from here
# 劈柴
'chop-wood'
# 到这就不能切了
Don't cut deeper when it reaches here
# 撕
Tear it apart
# 拢住了
Hold it tight
# 干烧冬笋有好多
There are a lot of restaurants
# 有好多社会餐饮也在做
that offer this dish
# 但是刀工处理上
But they always make mistakes
# 他的方法就错了
in terms of cutting the bamboo shoot
# 这叫劈柴块
This is the 'chop-wood' cut
# 这样做的最大好处 便于入味
The biggest advantage is for better flavor penetration
# 还有什么便于烹调
What else? For easy cooking
# 二伯点火
Er Bai, turn on the fire, please
# 二伯 你看都齐了
Er Bai, we have everything here
# 整齐了 刀工一致
Everything's ready. Uniformly cut
# 少搁一点盐入点味
Add some salt for the base flavor
# 掸点淀粉
Add some starch
# 搁这个淀粉以后炸出来有点虎皮色
In this way, the bamboo shoot becomes caramel brown after fried
# 这个感觉比较突出
That's gonna be great
# 这油啊 六成热了
The oil temperature is about 180 degrees Celsius
# 就上点颜色 外焦 脆嫩
Fry it for the color. Also it's gonna be crispy outside, while crunchy and tender inside
# 这炸着
While frying
# 咱把这盘也给它装好
Prepare the plate
# 这菜出来漂亮
The dish is gonna be beautiful
# 过去装饰都是自然的
In the past, we used natural materials for decoration
# 而且还可食的
The decorations were usually edible as well
# 底油
base oil
# 小料 葱 姜 蒜
Ingredients. Green onion, ginger, garlic
# 雪菜的梗
Stem of pickled potherb mustard
# 再来点水
Some water
# 酱油
Soysauce
# 黄酒
'Huangjiu' rice wine
# 老抽
dark soy sauce
# 白糖
Sugar
# 胡椒
Pepper
# 贼烫贼烫的
This is very hot
# 下锅以后再煨一煨
Braise it for some time after adding it into the wok
# 搁点水 因为火旺
Add some water. The heat is very powerful now
# 来点香油
Some sesame oil
# 这就行啦
That's it
# 来点明油
Some oil at last
# 好菜 一锅好菜
Nice dish. That's a nice one
# 干烧 没有汁儿
Dry-braise. No extra sauce
# 今天我觉得咱耍开了
Today we are playing it wild
# 颠起锅来了
I can toss the wok
# 尝尝
Taste it
# 太脆了 脆吧 太脆了
Too crunchy. Right? Incredibly crunchy
# 再来一根
One more
# 我给你带点雪里红梗
with some potherb mustard stem this time
# 再来一块
One more
# 隋坡也看半天了
Sui Po has been looking at it for a long time
# 隋坡 来
Sui Po, come on
# 这个笋味很香很脆
The bamboo shoot is very delicious and crunchy
# 再奖励一个
One more for you
# 雪里蕻
The pickled potherb mustard...
# 搁里边还有一个点缀的作用
is a perfect decoration for this dish
# 绿绿的
Green
# 入口呢还是脆的
and crunchy
# 曾经师父跟我说过一个
Previously my master told me
# 叫逢烧必炸
Braised food must be fried in advance
# 然后表面还掸了这些淀粉
Also, the starch on the surface
# 它遇热糊化之后
When the starch gelatinizes after heating
# 师父把这个汁儿往里一放
Master poured in the sauce
# 刚刚好表面的淀粉
The starch on the surface will
# 把汁吸完了 好看漂亮
absorb all the sauce. Looks beautiful
# 口感特别的清脆
The texture is extremely crunchy
# 你看这雪里蕻这叶啊
The potherb mustard leaves
# 经过这一炸 你看 酥脆
becomes very crispy after frying
# 因为冬笋它不易入味
Since it's hard for the bamboo shoot to absorb the flavors
# 搭着冬笋加上这个
The bamboo shoots and potherb mustard leaves
# 吃起来有一种酥香
match with each other to give a crispy,
# 脆嫩的感觉
crunchy and tender feeling
# 得掺着吃
You should enjoy them together
# 这也是一种点缀的方法
This is also one way of decorating the dish
# 叫可食
Edible decorations
# 你看见没有 没有一点糊弄的
See? Not careless at all
# 你看包括刀工的处理
Including cutting skills,
# 味道 形状 色彩
taste, shape, and color
# 其实是还原
This is to recover
# 原汁原味的过去40多年前的
The original dish
# 这种菜品
from more than 40 years ago
# 40年如一日
(Da Ye) has been working for 40 years,
# 兢兢业业
but has always been following the same principles
# 为烹调事业做贡献
and contributes to the cooking industry
# 高
That's marvelous
# 谢谢二伯
Thanks, Er Bai